בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Welcome to the last day of בבא בתרא
Bava Batra and of the בבות. Bavas. And we pick up on
the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה Mishna on קע"ה עמוד ב',
Kuf Ayin Hey Amud Bet, 175b. אמר עולא. Amar Ulla. So the
משנה Mishna just talked about the fact that what we've been assuming
for a while, that debts written with documents, a שטר חוב, shtar
chov, are debts that have liens, debts that are just oral with
witnesses but there's no written document, there are no liens. And then
there was a whole discussion about when the guarantor, the ערב, areiv,
signs at the bottom after the witnesses signed. The משנה Mishna says
he might be obligated, but there are no liens on his property,
on the guarantor's property. And בננס Banas said he's not even obligated.
So let's see with the very colorful
analogy at the end of the משנה. Mishna. So let's see the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר עולא דבר תורה אחד מלוה בשטר ואחד מלוה על
פה גובה מנכסים משועבדים. Amar Ulla, Dvar Torah, Echad Milveh Beshtar Ve'echad
Milveh Al Peh Goveh Minechasim Meshubadim. That there would really be liens,
you could collect from encumbered property whether it was with a document
or whether it was only oral, meaning only witnesses but no written
document. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? שעבודא דאורייתא. Shibuda De'oraisa.
No, maybe even if there are no witnesses, I mean, the guy
could deny it, and certainly the לקוחות Lokechos could deny it, but
at least in principle, right, he's not even requiring that. Liens are
from the תורה. Torah. The loan creates the reality of liens. You
don't need any other instrument to create the reality of liens. ואלא
מה טעמא אמרו מלוה על פה אינו גובה אלא מנכסים בני חורין?
Ve'ela Ma Ta'ama Amru Milveh Al Peh Eino Goveh Ela Minechasim Bnei
Chorin? So it must be the rabbis changed this. So what would
have motivated the rabbis to say that without a שטר, shtar, you're
only going to be able to collect from unencumbered property directly from
the לוה Lova and not from people that he sold to? משום
פסידא דלקוחות, Mishum Psed De'lokechos, to protect the people that purchased the
property from him. Okay, but it's the rabbis coming in and protecting
the purchasers and saying it's not fair to them if there's no
written evidence and no record and no way in which they could
find out. All right, אי הכי, Ei hachi, fine, אי הכי מלוה
בשטר נמי? Ei hachi milveh beshtar nami? So even with a written
document, let's protect them. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, התם אינהו דאפסידו אנפשייהו. Hasam inhu de'afsidu anafshayhu. No, there they
sort of, you know, they brought the loss upon themselves. They could
have had ways to have found out. Okay, but point of... I
mean, everybody agrees to the logic, which is the logic is a
written document people could find out and therefore they have responsibility to
find out and they should be aware. If it's not written then
that's not reasonable to expect that of them. But the question is
what is your point of departure and what's motivating you? So from
this perspective, the reality of the loan creates the lien. What's motivating
the rabbis to step in is to protect the לקוחות. Lokechos. They
see a need to do that when there is no written document
but not a need to do that when there is a written
document. Let's just wait to hear the other side of it. Okay,
that's what עולא Ulla says. ורבה אמר, Ve'Rabba Amar, and רבה Rabba
says no, דבר תורה, Dvar Torah, as far as the תורה Torah
is concerned, אחד מלוה בשטר ואחד מלוה על פה אינו גובה אלא
מנכסים בני חורין. Echad Milveh Beshtar Ve'echad Milveh Al Peh Eino Goveh
Ela Minechasim Bnei Chorin.
Whether in a שטר shtar and whether oral, you can only get
from the לוה. Lova. There's no reality of liens. Now by the
way, תוספות Tosafos points out רבה Rabba might not just be saying
by default that's the way it is. רבה Rabba might be saying
that even were you to write directly in the document, "I Michael
am borrowing from Dov and we testify that Michael borrowed from Dov
$10,000 and Michael agreed to have his property
encumbered and that Dov should have liens," it could be from the
תורה Torah that does nothing. Because maybe the idea of liens, not
just because we care about the people that are going to buy
the property and it's not fair to them, but the concept that
such a like a, you know, a phenomenon, a legal instrument should
exist, the legal reality that I have a right to this property
even after somebody else has bought it. Michael could sell his property,
he could give his property to me, but maybe there's no legal,
you know, there's no phenomenon of this thing called a lien that
I have a right to the property which will allow me to
collect it from somebody else after they've bought it from Michael. So
you know, no matter how much you tried, maybe the תורה Torah
doesn't even recognize it. All I have a right to do is
to collect from Michael.
Wait, you're saying somewhat of a halfway, you don't have a right...
I mean the תורה Torah doesn't even have someone else but you
have a right to collect my property from me.
Yeah, okay, but we're not discussing that. בני חורין Bnei Chorin means
I have a right to collect the property under your control, but
no liens, nothing that would enable me to collect it once it's
sold to somebody else. Okay, so that would be from the תורה's
Torah's perspective. ומה טעמא אמרו מלוה בשטר גובה מנכסים משועבדים? Ve'ma Ta'ama
Amru Milveh Beshtar Goveh Minechasim Meshubadim? So why therefore did the rabbis
come in and institute this thing called liens and do it with
a שטר? shtar? גובה מנכסים משועבדים, Goveh minechasim meshubadim, כדי שלא תנעול
דלת בפני לווין, kedei shelo tinol delas befnei lovin, so the flip
side of protecting the people that would purchase Michael's lands is to
not like not lock the door in front of people to lend
money. It's hard enough in הלכה Halacha to lend money. only negative
incentives to lend money unless you're operating with like a היתר עסקה
Heter Iska or something. So therefore the Rabbis had to do things
to encourage people to lend money so that I want to get
my money back the Rabbis had to give you some liens on
Michael's property to ensure that I could get the money back after
he sold his property. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי ei
hachi if that's true מלוה על פה נמי, milve al pe nami,
so let's give lenders even without a שטר shtar the right let's
give them liens so that they can get their money back. So
the גמרא Gemara says, התם לית ליה קלא hasam leis lei kala
no there there's no voice there's nobody knows about it and again
meaning there the פסידא דלקוחות psida dilokuchos concern would kick in. And
as to the claim and and by the way since the whole
incentive is to
make
it easier for me to lend money once I have an option
available to me right with a שטר shtar we don't have to
give me all the options right we just say write with a
שטר shtar and therefore you know it'll go ahead and and I
have the way of doing it and protecting myself. Maybe there's a
question about who pays for the שטר shtar we actually had that
discussion earlier. You get the borrowers to pay for the שטר shtar
then that makes it that much more of a you know of
a not of a removal of an obstacle since there's an option
for me to lend money and to know that I'll have liens.
Yes דאורייתא de-oraita
does the מלוה malveh have rights to just the
person's either way cash and not the property or property and not
the cash?
No so there's a little bit of a hint to that in
the רשב"ם Rashbam but I'm going to go with תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות
Tosafot assumes no. Even if שעבוד לאו דאורייתא shibud lav de-oraita all
that means is this type of a right that would allow me
to collect once the property isn't in the person's hands. But as
long as the property is in the person's hands whether שעבוד דאורייתא
shibud de-oraita or לאו דאורייתא lav de-oraita or whatever that's all part
of the fact that you owe me money. Okay? And you owe
me now and you owe me now of course there is an
interesting issue the גמרא Gemara discusses does you owe me money mean
therefore I can compel you to pay with what any property you
have land property your automobile you know your baseball cards whatever but
ultimately it's through your personal obligation to me and I can compel
you to pay from any of your property. You don't need the
idea of lien there but that's the nature of your obligation to
me or does it mean remember the גמרא Gemara introduced the idea
the other day the idea of ערבות areivut that your property is
like your guarantor? So let's say you're off in France or whatever.
I'm not compelling you. I'm just going to the בית דין Beit
Din and they're letting me go into your house and take my
collection you know. So that is a right to your property maybe
as a type of a guarantor but still it's not going to
the point of liens which is a right to do it once
it's in somebody else's hands. But you're right conceptually there are three
levels okay? There's the לוה's loveh obligation directly to me which is
means that I can bring him to court and make him make
him pay cash or maybe I can compel him to pay anything
but that's at least when I'm engaging the לוה. loveh. Right? Then
there is you know the לוה loveh is is alive but he's
not present okay and in that type of a case you know
but still the לוה's loveh property and in that type of case
can I go straight to the property? So that maybe is an
idea of liens but maybe that's an idea like the גמרא Gemara
said before of like that they're his guarantors you know and then
the idea of liens is can I take the property when it's
in somebody else's possession? That somebody else could be a person he
sold it to could be his heirs but that completely it's not
in the context of my relationship with the לוה loveh and the
property is not even any longer the לוה's loveh and that seems
to be the case we're focusing on.
There's also זיבורית ובינונית ziborit u'beinonit like what kind of property.
Yeah yeah all those are different considerations.
One question kind of about we're starting to say like כל קלא
kol kala but how does that I guess harmonize or not with
like other things we see in the גמרא Gemara like חברא דחברא
אית ליה chavera dechavera itlei וחברא דחברא אית ליה. vachavera dechavera itlei.
So the גמרא Gemara discusses the גמרא Gemara discusses that it depends
on also like like the difference between by the way of a
you know about if somebody's on my property whether I hear about
somebody being on my property has to do fact that people know
it's relevant to me so they know to report it to me
whereas if you borrowed money from me people don't know to report
it to Chanan right would people tell Chanan about that okay and
now Chanan wants to buy property from you you know so he
wasn't yet a person of interest that the message should get to
him but anyway there are different types of חשבון cheshbon whatever there
are different types of maybe but not all rumors are everybody's everybody's
is like clued into and not all rumors are as juicy as
other rumors. Yes an example yesterday with the oral contract we
didn't have any didn't have any right to claim the land.
No no no well that's what was a little Michael's discussing before
it might be that the person is believed to say he paid
up okay but that's different from whether I have שעבודים shibudim right
I could have שעבודים shibudim but it'll be a moot point if
the guy just lies and says he paid up or it could
be that the that the purchasers would be in a position to
say right you know like prove to me that you lent that
money if I don't have witnesses because how can you come collect
it from me? I don't care that the לוה loveh admits he
borrowed the money that's not good enough to make me give you
the property you're going to have to bring objective evidence so all
those are things to consider but if you have that type of
evidence the question still would be would there be שעבודים shibudim without
about the written document. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
ומי אמר רבה הכי? U'mi amar Rabba hachi? Now, did רבה Rabba
really say this that from the תורה's Torah perspective there are no
loans? No liens, excuse me. והאמר רבה, V'ha'amar Rabba, didn't רבה Rabba
say גבו קרקע יש לו, גבו מעות אין לו? Gavu karka yesh
lo, gavu ma'ot ein lo? So now the גמרא Gemara is going,
it's like a little pop quiz at the end of the מסכת
Masechet to see how much you remember from things we discussed before.
So here's a discussion about when does a בכור Bechor get a
double portion?
So of course you all remember the principle that אין הבכור נוטל
פי שנים בראוי כבמוחזק, Ein habechor notel pi shnayim b'ra'uy k'bemuchzak, that
a בכור—you Bechor see Michael remembers it, so Michael gets an A—so
a בכור Bechor does not get a double portion on things that
were coming into the estate, only things that the father had before
he died. So the big question is, what about outstanding debts? Outstanding
debts that get paid after the father died. Does the בכור Bechor
get that double or not? Is that like that was already money
in the estate? So רבה Rabba said it depends how those debts
were paid up. If those debts were paid up with land, then
it's like that was always in the estate and the בכור Bechor
gets double. If they were paid up with cash, then it's new
money coming into the estate. So what's the logical difference? Either way,
it was money owed and then it was finally paid. The only
logic to say that the land is like it was always part
of the estate and the בכור Bechor gets double is if you
think there's an idea of שעבוד Shibud and that there's a reality
of a lien, and therefore that lien creates that like the estate
already had its claws into that land and maybe it was already
in the process of taking full possession of it. Okay, now that
makes sense if שעבוד Shibud is דאורייתא, D'Oraita, but if it's דרבנן,
D'Rabbanan, why should the בכור Bechor on the basis of this principle
get double? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא איפוך, V'chi
teima ipoch, maybe I should reverse it, maybe with money he gets
double because that's like a reversal, money was lent, money was paid
back, it's like it was always there, but with קרקע Karka not,
in order to make רבה Rabba consistent with what he said. Okay,
the גמרא Gemara says no, because we also have a challenge with
עולא. Ulla. וכי תימא איפוך דרבה לעולא ועולא לרבה, V'chi teima ipoch
d'Rabba l'Ulla v'Ulla l'Rabba, oh, now not only maybe reverse the בכור
Bechor ruling, reverse the רבה Rabba and עולא Ulla position here on
whether liens are דאורייתא. D'Oraita. No, because we have another evidence that
shows that עולא Ulla holds like he—like we know, like he says
here—that liens are from the תורה. Torah. How do you know that?
והאמר עולא, V'ha'amar Ulla, דבר תורה, Devar Torah, בעל חוב דינו בזיבורית,
Ba'al chov dino b'ziborit, that from the תורה's Torah perspective, a בעל
חוב Ba'al chov gets from the grade C property. Now, how does
that prove that עולא Ulla holds that there are liens in the
תורה? Torah? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, well, because he's getting property.
But תוספות Tosafot says, and this gets back to Michael's question before,
but that could mean when he's getting property from directly the לווה.
Lova. When I'm forcing Michael to pay and Michael has property in
his name, can I go to the court and say I want
his best property? And עולא Ulla says no, Michael's entitled to give
you his worst property. But that's not a proof of a lien,
that's just Michael owes me the money. That's not telling you what
happens when the land gets sold elsewhere. So תוספות Tosafot doesn't really
know why the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is proof that עולא
Ulla holds of such an idea of liens. The רשב"ם Rashbam thinks
that the concept of liens is relevant even when I'm directly collecting
from Michael. Maybe anything I'm getting from Michael that isn't cash shows
a direct right to his property. That seems to be the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam understands it. Okay, but for whatever reason, the גמרא
Gemara thinks that this is proof that עולא Ulla holds that there
are liens in the תורה. Torah. Okay, so clearly רבה Rabba holds
there aren't. So if רבה Rabba holds there aren't liens in the
תורה, Torah, why when you collect property does the בכור Bechor get
a double portion? So the
גמרא Gemara says, רבה טעמא דבני מערבא קאמר ולאו סבירא ליה. Rabba
ta'ama d'vnei Ma'arava ka'amar v'lav sevira leh. Yeah, רבה Rabba over there
was explaining the position of בני מערבא. Bnei Ma'arava. That was a
discussion there about what did בני מערבא Bnei Ma'arava say, when does
a בכור Bechor get double, when he doesn't. So רבה Rabba was
explaining their position, but he himself would not hold that. He would
not hold that קרקע Karka gives you more right than money when
it comes to the בכור. Bechor. Now I do want to pause
for a moment
that idea of גבו קרקע Gavu karka the בכור Bechor gets double
was explaining בני מערבא, Bnei Ma'arava, wasn't his position. Now I just
want to pause for a moment and say
it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara thinks here that there would
be a practical difference between רבה Rabba and עולא, Ulla, because you
could say what they're all debating is just a historical theoretical discussion,
right? But practically once the rabbis instituted, in this case you have
liens, in this case you don't, whether they're giving liens that the
תורה Torah didn't give, or whether they're taking away liens that the
תורה Torah gave, at the end of the day we all agree
that the same legal system obtains, right? There's no maybe residue of
that difference. It seems like the גמרא Gemara understands that if you
understand that the liens are from the תורה, Torah, somehow conceptually
they are more powerful than if those liens were only given to
you from the rabbis, right? Because if they are liens from the
תורה, Torah, then the estate collected it, it's like the estate always
had it and the בכור Bechor gets double. But if the liens
were only from the rabbis and the estate collected it, it would
not be like the estate always had it. It's not so obvious
why that's true. One interesting way to conceptualize this difference, and I
should mention this as well because it gets to something the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* isn't saying, but a way to understand the power of
a שטר shtar, *shtar* in creating liens, is how much do you
conceptualize liens as a partial ownership in the land or a right
in the land itself, you know, and I'm exercising my ownership of
the land, you know, my right in under these conditions and now
it's like this land was always mine and so on or, you
know, whatever it was always like I had my claws in that
land. Or is it just an abstract right, but it's not a
sense of a partial ownership of the land itself. And if you
think of it as a partial ownership of the land itself, then
that could be what a שטר shtar, *shtar* does, because a שטר
shtar *shtar* is a way of transferring land. So maybe the שטר
חוב shtar chov *shtar chov* what it does is it transfers the
rights in the property and creates a partial ownership of that property.
So the way some ראשונים Rishonim. *Rishonim* אחרונים *Acharonim* explain it, this
isn't in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* all
makes it about whether you're protecting the borrowers or not protecting the
borrowers, but they say that there's two ways of conceptualizing liens. Just
an abstract right, Michael owes me money, that gives me a right
to go to חנן Chanan *Chanan*, you know, that doesn't seem really
fair to חנן *Chanan*. Why does the fact that he owes me
money and I have some right let me go to property he
owns? It's much easier to understand it if we say all along
I had a certain right to that land and when he bought
it he bought it with my rights already present in that land.
But if you understand it that way, then you could sort of
say that maybe that's what the שטר shtar *shtar* helps me do.
The שטר shtar *shtar* is a way of transferring land and therefore
transferring rights to land. Okay, so maybe that has to do also
with this difference of whether שיעבוד *shibud* was דאורייתא d'oraisa *De-Oraita* or
whether it was created from the Rabbis, how sort of deep you
feel my שיעבוד
*shibud* is, because here it's clear that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying that whether it's דאורייתא d'oraisa. *De-Oraita* or דרבנן drabbanan. *De-Rabbanan* would
have a practical, you know, legal implication in terms of this issue
of בכור *bechor*. Yes? What kind of property bought? Was it זיבורית
*ziborit* or בינונית *beinonit* or עידית *idit*?
What do you mean? If the בעל חוב *ba'al chov* is גובה
*goveh* זיבורית *ziborit*? Yeah, then he sold חנן *Chanan* like grade-A property
then? Well, that's a קשיא *kushya* anyway, but that's not relevant to
this question.
I mean, whatever, however the חז"ל *Chazal* limited
it, that's how they limited it. I mean, yes, property taxes, I
mean like if the taxes go up? Yeah, well, there was from
the government, not from הלכה halacha *Halacha*. That would be a question
about what the government would, how the secular government would conceptualize this.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, now
רב ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel, דאמרי תרווייהו *Rav u-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu*, now רב
ושמואל Rav u'Shmuel *Rav u-Shmuel* both say מלווה על פה al peh,
אינו גובה לא מן היורשים ולא מן הלקוחות *malveh al peh eino
goveh lo min ha-yorshim ve-lo min ha-lekuchot*. Now we're going to see
another way in which they use
this question of is it from
the תורה Torah, *Torah*, from the Rabbis with a practical legal implication.
They both say that if it's an oral loan, you don't get
either
from the heirs or from the buyers. Why? מאי mai? טעמא שיעבודא
shibuda לאו דאורייתא lav d'oraisa? *mai ta'ama shibuda lav de-oraita*. The שיעבוד
*shibud* isn't דאורייתא d'oraisa *De-Oraita*, it only exists where the Rabbis created
it, and they only created it when there's a written document, when
there's a שטר shtar *shtar*. So the point is you don't even
get it from the heirs, right? Now think for a moment. You
can't force the heirs to pay their father's debt if there's no
written document.
Now if you think about it, if basically we're only trying to
protect, really by the
fact that you have a loan gives you שיעבודים *shibudim*, gives you
liens.
But the Rabbis to protect the innocent purchasers said we'll erase them
when there's no written document. Well, that shouldn't apply to a case
of heirs because the heirs aren't people that are choosing to buy
the property and putting out their own money to buy the property,
they're just, you know, receiving it. So since they're just receiving it
and I actually have those liens and I put out money and
lent the money and I want to get my loan paid off,
then I should be able to collect from the heirs. That's if
you were to say that שיעבוד *shibud* is דאורייתא d'oraisa, *De-Oraita*, right?
Then therefore there's no reason to protect the heirs and therefore even
if it was just an oral loan I should be able to
collect. Whereas if you say that שיעבוד *shibud* is not דאורייתא d'oraisa,
*De-Oraita* and the Rabbis came ahead and instituted it to, why did
they institute it? To encourage me to lend money, then I had
the option of writing a שטר shtar *shtar* and I should have
written a שטר shtar *shtar* in the first place and because that's
what they gave me to allow me to encourage me, and if
I didn't write a שטר shtar *shtar* and I was willing to
risk my right to collect it from the purchasers, then I've also
given up my right to collect it from the heirs. So that's
what they say. Okay, so let's read that again. רב ושמואל Rav
u'Shmuel דאמרי תרווייהו *Rav u-Shmuel de-amri tarvaihu* מלווה על פה al peh
*malveh al peh* if it's oral אינו גובה לא מן היורשים ולא
מן הלקוחות *eino goveh lo min ha-yorshim ve-lo min ha-lekuchot*. You can't
even get it from the heirs, you can't get it from the
לקוחות lakochot *lekuchot* is obvious. מאי טעמא שיעבודא לאו דאורייתא lav d'oraisa.
*mai ta'ama shibuda lav de-oraita*. It's not from the תורה Torah *Torah*,
we only created it when there was a written document to encourage
people to lend money. You chose not to use the written document,
you lost out and you can't even collect it from the heirs.
ורבי יוחנן וריש לקיש דאמרי תרווייהו *Ve-Rabbi Yochanan ve-Resh Lakish de-amri tarvaihu*,
they both say מלווה על פה גובה בין מן היורשים ובין מן
הלקוחות *malveh al peh goveh bein min ha-yorshim u-vein min ha-lekuchot*. But
they go the opposite. which is not what our משנה teaches, like
it's crazy. This is against everything we've ever learned. They're saying you
can get it even from purchasers if there's no written document. Okay,
my טעם taam it's שיעבודא דאורייתא. shibuda d'oraisa. It's דאורייתא d'oraisa and
the rabbis actually didn't do anything to interfere with it. Okay, so
this is the actual nice middle ground position is not being said
here. The logical middle ground position is, if it's על פה, you
can't collect from the לקוחות lakochot because they're not protected, but you
can collect from the heirs because there's no need to protect the
heirs. And that makes a lot of sense if שיעבודא is דאורייתא.
d'oraisa. Okay, רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish are
going to the extreme and they're saying that you can always collect
from לקוחות lakuchos even without a written document. That's nothing we've ever
said before. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it. מיתיבי
Meisive says הגמרא haGemara asks on this, החופר בור ברשות הרבים, hachofer
bor b'reshus harabim, somebody is digging a well in רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, so ראובן Reuven there at the bottom of the well that
he is that he is illegally digging in the public thoroughfare, ונפל
עליו שור והרגו, v'nafal alav shor v'harago, and an ox walks into
the pit, falls down and kills him in the process. פטור, Patur,
the owner of the ox is exempt from paying any damages or
כופר. kofer. כופר, Kofer, not only that, ולא עוד, v'lo od, אלא
שאם מת, ela she'im meis, if ראובן Reuven died in the process,
השור המית השור, hashor hamis hashor, excuse me, it says it twice,
point is, if the ox died, yeah ראובן Reuven we're going to
assume is dead, if the ox died, יורשי בעל הבור חייבין לשלם,
yorshei baal habor chayavin l'shalem, the heirs of ראובן's Reuven's kids have
to pay, have to pay the owners of the ox דמי שור
לבעליו. d'mei shor l'baalav. Okay, so now that's a very nice colorful
case. I'm sure you'll go home and remember that, the ox that
falls on the guy and his heirs have to pay the owner
of the ox. But the point is, why do they have to
pay? That's a מלוה על פה. milveh al peh. There's no written
document. What? Not a מלוה, milveh, it's a חוב על פה. chov
al peh. Okay, which by the way is another interesting נפקא מינה
nafka mina that we haven't discussed, which is if the whole purpose
of creating it was כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני לוין, k'dei shelo
tinol deles bifnei lovin, do you have liens when you're not dealing
with loans, right? So תוספות Tosafot sort of says yes, but again,
that could have been something we could have explored. אי נמי, Ei
nami, but the גמרא Gemara is assuming that it would be any
debt is the same. Okay, now you could have again challenged that.
If the whole reason is שלא תנעול דלת, shelo tinol deles, maybe
we don't create liens even with written documents when it's not in
the context of loans. But we're going to bracket that. Okay, and
we're going to assume debts and loans are all the same. So
now, but why can you collect money from the heirs? Okay, why,
I mean, you know, there's no written document. So, if you say
that that's a question according to, I guess רב ושמואל, Rav u'Shmuel.
because רב Rav ושמואל says you can't collect from the heirs without
a written document. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב עילא אמר
רב Amar Rav Ila amar Rav בשעמד בדין. b'she'amad b'din. So the
case is ראובן Reuven didn't die right away. They took ראובן Reuven
to a court case for their ox and there he was in
the hospital bed, but they took him to the court case and
then he died later. And since בית דין פסקו דין, Beis Din
pasku din, that's like a written document, that's a public thing and
that's like a written document. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא והרגו
קתני? v'ha v'harago katani? But it says it says they killed ראובן.
Reuven. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava שנעשה
טרפה. shenasa treifah. Yeah, yeah, yeah, whatever, they they fatally wounded him
and then he died later. It's like that Monty Python skit, "I'm
not dead yet!" Okay, so so there he was. He wasn't dead
yet and then they got and then they had a דין. din.
And therefore it was like they got a written document. ואמרי רב
נחמן V'amri Rav Nachman תני תנא מת וקברו. tani tana meis u'kvaro.
What do you mean? But רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that the
תנא tana teaches ראובן Reuven died and the ox buried him in
the process, like the ox fell on him in the well and
and they just left him in the well and they buried him
there in the well. So the גמרא Gemara says, התם דיתבי דייני
אפומא דבירא וחייבוהו. hasam d'yasvi dayanei apuma d'veira v'chayivuhu. Yeah, but there
was a בית דין Beis Din sitting right at the edge of
the well. And before ראובן's Reuven's last breath went out of him,
they פסקו. pasku. Okay, that's obviously a pretty absurd case. Anyway, in
other places the גמרא Gemara actually speaks about מלוה הכתובה בתורה ככתובה
בשטר דמיא, milveh haksuvah baTorah k'ksuvah b'shtar damya, that it could be
that a debt that
a debt that exists
based on a Torah obligation like paying for damages, it's like it
exists in a document. Okay, but again the question would still be,
you know, you know about about like how now are you collecting
from the heirs? So once once more רב Rav ושמואל say that
if there's no document, you don't collect from the heirs. Here it
seems that you do. The גמרא Gemara gives a pretty absurd way
to explain why they could collect from the heirs according to רב
Rav ושמואל. Elsewhere the גמרא Gemara, might explain that it might be
different because it's based on a debt that's in the Torah, as
it were, the obligation to pay off for damages. Okay, and ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan hold something that goes
against everything we know and they say even without a document you
can always collect liens. As I said, the more reasonable middle position
is that without a document, without a שטר, shtar, you can collect
from the heirs but not from the buyers. Okay, understand? Why don't
they say תיובתא tiyuvta or something? I don't know what to say.
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, so רב פפא Rav Papa says
הלכתא, hilchasa, דף פ"ה עמוד ב', daf peh hei amud beis, the
last דף daf of the מסכת, masechet, the הלכה halakha is מלוה
על פה גובה. milveh al peh goveh. Reasonable middle position is that
without a document, without a שטר, shtar you can collect from the
heirs but not from the buyers. Okay? I understand. Why don't they
say like תוספות Tosafos there's one פשט? pshat? It's like, I mean
obviously they, I don't know what to say. אמר רב פפא, Amar
Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa says הלכתא, Hilchasa, דף קעו,
Daf Kuf-Ayin-Vav, the last דף daf of the מסכת. masechet. The הלכה
is מלוה על פה milveh al peh גובה מן היורשים goveh min
hayorshim ואינו גובה מן הלקוחות, ve'eino goveh min halakuchos, which is thank
you, the reasonable position. גובה מן היורשים כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני
לווין. goveh min hayorshim kedei shelo tin'ol deles bifnei lovin. You collect
from the heirs so as not to lock the door in front
of lenders, even though you could say the lenders should have written
a שטר shtar if they wanted to protect their interests. Nevertheless, maybe,
you know, a guy dying and the heirs inheriting is a more
natural thing and it's a regular thing, and therefore we want a
lender to have a regular way of collecting and maybe it's more
fair that the heirs are paying the estate, you know, their father's
debt. So there we sort of say in order to encourage people,
we'll allow you to collect even if you didn't write a document
because it's from the heirs and they didn't put out any money.
ואינו גובה מן הלקוחות, ve'eino goveh min halakuchos, one minute, but you
don't collect from the buyers. דלית ליה קלא, de'leis lei kala, because
the buyers aren't—for the normal reasons, the buyers aren't protected. Now is
it clear how רב פפא Rav Pappa holds whether שעבודא דאורייתא shibuda
d'oraisa or לאו דאורייתא? Well, if it's דאורייתא you'd definitely be גובה
מן היורשים. goveh min hayorshim No, not necessarily. Well you are גובה
מן היורשים, goveh min hayorshim. yes. Okay, but it's not clear which
way he holds. He gives a reason that could explain why we
either took it away, you know, why we removed the—maybe basically שעבודא
דאורייתא, shibuda d'oraisa, but we removed it when it's על פה from
the לקוחות lakuchos. to protect the לקוחות. lakuchos Or basically שעבודא לאו
דאורייתא, shibuda lav d'oraisa, right? But we put it in in the
case of heirs כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני לווין. kedei shelo tin'ol
deles bifnei lovin. He gives a reason for both sides, so he's
not taking a position on שעבודא דאורייתא. shibuda d'oraisa. תוספות Tosafos points
out that elsewhere the גמרא Gemara sort of sees this as maybe
taking a position on that issue. If you look at תוספות, Tosafos,
גובה מן היורשים goveh min hayorshim, כדי שלא תנעול דלת בפני לווין.
kedei shelo tin'ol deles bifnei lovin. תוספות Tosafos says הכא מוקי אהא
מלוה אליבא דכולי עלמא, hacha moki aha milveh aliba d'chulei alma, בין
למאן דאמר דאורייתא בין למאן דאמר לאו דאורייתא. bein leman de'amar d'oraisa
bein leman de'amar lav d'oraisa. So this split that you collect from
heirs with an oral thing and not from the purchasers, you know,
you can explain it whichever whatever your point of departure is. ובפרק
קמא דקידושין אמר גובה מן היורשים שעבודא דאורייתא, uv'perek kama de'kiddushin amar
goveh min hayorshim shibuda d'oraisa, ואינו גובה מן הלקוחות ve'eino goveh min
halakuchos etc. So the גמרא Gemara. there sides with the position שעבודא
דאורייתא, shibuda d'oraisa, right? Which makes sense and to say since שעבודא
דאורייתא shibuda d'oraisa fundamentally you're entitled to the heirs and we're only
going to, you know, say you can't get it from the לקוחות
lakuchos, because we have to protect them, but we don't have to
protect the heirs because the heirs aren't spending any money. All right,
but there's a way you could sort of say you can't box
me in. This split decision, you get it from the heirs and
not from the לקוחות, lakuchos. could be explained according to either side,
yes. Is the שטר shtar a rabbinic invention? The idea, so that's
a good question, that's an excellent question. Is the idea of a
שטר חוב shtar chov a rabbinic invention? I mean the גמרא Gemara
learns that for example that, you know, from the book of ירמיהו,
Yirmiyahu, you know, כתב בספר וחתום והעד עדים, kasav b'sefer v'chasom v'ha'ed
edim, you know, whatever, which is actually about a sale document of
a, of what do you call it, of a field. It could
be that the idea of a שטר shtar which serves as an
instrument, an instrument for divorce or an instrument for transac—for, you know,
selling the land, effecting the transaction, those are דאורייתא, certainly a גט
get is. But a שטר shtar that is purely written as a
שטר ראיה, shtar re'aya, as a שטר shtar that is to bring
evidence to the fact that something occurred, right, it could be that
that is purely—there's a whole discussion of רמב"ן Ramban and רמב"ם, Rambam,
you've hit on a major major debate of ראשונים. It could be
that that is only rabbinic, because biblically speaking if you want testimony
you've got to show up in court and give your testimony. And
the idea that you're going to write a שטר Shtar, whose whole
purpose is to sort of like, you know, concretize, you know, like,
you know, make the testimony exist in writing without it being produced
in a, you know, and without it being produced in a court,
it could be that that is a rabbinic institution. That's debated. Whether
שטר קנין, shtar kinyan, a שטר Shtar that effects a change, a
גט, get, a writ of manumission to free a slave, a writ
to buy a plot of land, a writ that would actually effect
קידושין, kiddushin, קידושין kiddushin could be by שטר, Shtar those are דאורייתא,
whether a שטר Shtar? whose whole purpose is just to provide testimony,
that is debatable whether that's דאורייתא or דרבנן. Okay? But you're right,
here because you're saying if it's not—here we're assuming that the difference
of a שטר Shtar, is a rabbinic difference, and that's consistent with
the idea that a שטר Shtar might be—the whole שטר Shtar might
be a rabbinic institution. That is a good point. Okay, so anyway
we have that very nice classic debate if שעבודא דאורייתא shibuda d'oraisa
or לאו דאורייתא. The nice important conclusion when it comes to heirs,
that even if it's not a שטר Shtar. you still have liens,
okay, without the גמרא Gemara concluding which side of the debate that
comes down on, but as תוספות Tosafos points out from another גמרא,
Gemara there's reason to think that that's more consistent with the idea
that שעבודא shibuda is דאורייתא. And therefore it'll exist even without a
שטר Shtar in the case of the heirs, but it won't exist
for the לקוחות. lekuchos Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. הוציא עליו כתב ידו שהוא חייב לו גובה מנכסים בני חורין.
Hotzi alav ktav yado shehu chayav lo gove min-nechasim bnei chorin. If
you have witnesses without a שטר, shtar you don't have liens, and
if you have a שטר shtar without witnesses, you don't have liens.
What's a שטר shtar without witnesses? You've got the borrower's own hand-written
IOU. So you can use that to collect from the borrower, but
that doesn't create liens for the purchasers. בעי מיניה רבה בר רב
נחמן מרב יוחנן. Ba'ei minei Rabba bar Rav Nachman me-Rav Yochanan. So
he asked of Yochanan. הוחזק כתב ידו בבית דין מאי? Huchzak ktav
yado be-veis din mai? So what if the כתב יד ktav yad
was already established in בית דין, beis din, which means Michael has
this thing, "I hereby, I borrowed a thousand dollars from Dove, signed
Michael Waxman," I go to a בית דין beis din and say,
"Guys, can you go ahead and validate this signature for me and
write your הנפק," hanpek, you know, write your validation on it that
says that you've seen that this is Michael's signature and you established
it? And now when it comes time to collect, I won't have
to go through that whole process. And they say, "Sure Dove, no
problem," and they go ahead, they validate the signature and they write
their seal. Does that seal of בית דין beis din become now
like עדים edim on the שטר? shtar, And now it becomes עדים
edim on the שטר, shtar I now have liens on Michael's property.
You understand the question? 'Cause I now got three people to validate
Michael's signature. Okay, מאי? So אמר ליה אף על פי שהוחזק כתב
ידו בבית דין אינו גובה אלא מנכסים בני חורין. Amar lei af
al pi she-huchzak ktav yado be-veis din eino gove ela mi-nechasim bnei
chorin. I'm sorry, that does not create liens. Liens on it is
not testified by witnesses. Now one of the reasons might be, not
only because the בית דין beis din isn't functioning as witnesses to
the original loan, but one of the reasons might be because it's
coming after the loan and the document existed, right? So it's like,
you know, so it's not go, I mean, that's an interesting question,
like what if you sort of, you know, did it sort of
after the שטר shtar was already created? But anyway, but also they're
not directly functioning like that. Okay, so he says, let me just
read the רשב"ם Rashbam here. Okay, let's read a little bit more
in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. מתיב זעירי בר חמא. Masiv Ze'iri bar
Chama. So זעירי בר חמא Ze'iri bar Chama asks on this. שלשה
גיטין פסולים ואם נישאת הולד כשר. Shlosha gittin psulin ve-im niseis ha-valad
kasher. There are three types of גיטין gittin which are rabbinically invalid,
but בדיעבד be-di'avad if the woman gets married we won't say that
the kid is a ממזר, mamzer, we'll recognize that it's legitimate. What
are they? ואלו הן: כתב בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים. Ve-eilu hen:
kasav bi-ktav yado ve-ein alav edim. It was hand-written by the husband
and no witnesses are on it. יש עליו עדים ואין בו זמן,
Yesh alav edim ve-ein bo zman, or there were witnesses but there
was no time in it. יש בו זמן ואין בו אלא עד
אחד, Yesh bo zman ve-ein bo ela ed echad, or there were
witnesses and a time written in the document or date, I should
say, written in the document, but there's really only one witness. הרי
אלו שלשה גיטין פסולים ואם נישאת הולד כשר. Harei elu shlosha gittin
psulin ve-im niseis ha-valad kasher. So that's good, but it's, you know,
those are פסול, pasul, but בדיעבד be-di'avad if the woman uses it,
the child is, it's a good גט get and the child is
not a ממזר. mamzer. רבי אלעזר אומר. Rabbi Elazar omer. רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says, אף על פי שאין עליו עדים אלא שנתנו לו
בפני עדים כשר וגובה מנכסים משועבדים. Af al pi she-ein alav edim
ela she-nasnu lo bifnei edim kasher ve-gove mi-nechasim mshubadim. Even if there
were no witnesses, but it was given in front of witnesses, because
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar you might remember is the position עדי מסירה
כרתי. eidei mesira karsi. The witnesses who observe the שטר shtar being
handed over, the גט get being handed over, become the witnesses of
the שטר. shtar, So he says that would totally be כשר לכתחילה.
kasher le-chatchila. And not only that, and here's the line that's relevant
for us, if it were not a גט get but a שטר
shtar חוב and Michael handed me his document that he owes me
a thousand dollars and there were no witnesses at all and wasn't
even his handwriting, he ran it off of his printer, okay? But
the two of you saw it, you become the witnesses in the
שטר shtar and now I can collect, I have liens. So that's
by the way a fascinating idea for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar because
if the whole idea of a witness שטר shtar. is that it
creates a קול, kol, even though the שטר shtar itself isn't signed,
you guys just saw it being handed over, that creates a שטר
shtar that creates liens. Okay, that's רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar position. Why
is this relevant for us? 'Cause we're assuming if when the two
of you saw the שטר, shtar you know, even though it wasn't
written in the שטר shtar the testimony, that creates liens, so when
I go ahead and I take the שטר shtar to a בית
דין beis din and get the בית דין beis din to look
at it and to validate it, then that's three, that should certainly
create liens if they validate it. Why should it be different? So
the גמרא Gemara says it is different. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, שאני התם דמשעת כתיבה הוא דשיעבד נפשיה. Shani hasam de-mishas ktiva
hu de-shiebbed nafshia. No, no, no, there, the liens existed from the
time the שטר shtar was written. What does that mean? It means
when you two, חנן and דוד, Dovid, you witness Michael giving over
the שטר, shtar, you are the witnesses in the document. So the
שטר shtar. when it first existed, when did the שטר shtar first
exist? When it was handed to me, that's when it gets the
status of the שטר. shtar When it's handed to the other side,
it had witnesses, when it came into effect it had witnesses. When
it came into effect it was a שטר shtar, with עדים. edim.
That's the case when there was nothing written but there were two
witnesses present at the time. However, when Michael hands me his hand-written
IOU and I go and an hour later to בית דין beis
din and I knock on their door and I get them to
validate it, the שטר shtar became active without witnesses. And since it
became active without witnesses and the witnesses were only placed on later,
then that is not a שטר shtar, that creates liens. Okay, do
you understand? It's like a formalistic difference. We're not dealing with technically
how public of a matter it is. but the שטר shtar. that
creates liens is a שטר shtar that was a שטר shtar. when
it was turned into a שטר, shtar, when it was handed over
to the other side. So even if the witnesses aren't written in
and they're standing and observing, that's a שטר. shtar However, if it's
Michael signature, and the signature is validated later, but when it was
handed to me, it did not—there were no witnesses in it, that
is not a שטר shtar, and there are no liens as a
result of it. דיני שטרות? Dinei Shtaros? Exactly. Okay, okay. If you
take a look at the רשב"ם Rashbam for example, he says like
this: דכל שטר—it's dechol shtar 1, 2, 3, about 7 lines down
in the narrow lines, he says: דכל שטר מלוה ומכירה שכותבין בו
עדים, dechol shtar milve umechira shekotvin bo eidim, if the שטר shtar,
has witnesses in it, whether they're written in it or whether they
exist in it because of רבי אלעזר's Rebbi Elazar idea of עדי
מסירה כרתי, eidei mesira karsai, גובים ממשועבדים, govin mimshubadim, כאילו כתב בהן
אחריות, keilu kasav bahen achrayus, that you can use to collect with
liens, like it's written in. או דלמא קיום שטר אינו מועיל לשום
שטר—this o dilma kiyum shtar eino moil leshum shtar is the question,
but he'll articulate why it shouldn't work. או דלמא קיום שטר אינו
מועיל לשום שטר אלא להחזיקו בבית דין—all o dilma kiyum shtar eino
moil leshum shtar ela lehachziko beveis din a validation does is it
just says, "This is a good שטר," shtar but it's not adding
to its weight. It's recognizing that it was Michael's signature, but it
doesn't give more weight to it than it had before. ולכן כאילו
ימסרו עדים או לאו ולא יוכל לטעון שטר זה מזויף הוא דבית
דין קיימוהו וידעו המלווה. velachen keilu yimsru eidim o lav velo yuchal
liton shtar ze mizuyaf hu debeis din kiyumuhu veyadu hamalveh. וגם זה
לא יגבה אלא מבני חורין. vegam ze lo yigbe ela mibnei chorin.
ולהכי אהני בית דין, ulehachi ahani beis din, the בית דין beis
din only helps so יכל לומר אין זה כתב ידי, yuchal lomar
ein ze kesav yadi, that you can't deny that it's your witnesses.
Meaning, that's another way of emphasizing what I was emphasizing, which was
when the שטר shtar became a שטר, shtar did it have witnesses
in it or not, or were the witnesses like, I don't know,
added later because the בית דין beis din signed later. But this
is a bit—which is sort of a little bit the way the
גמרא Gemara articulates it at the end, like משעת כתיבה, mishas kesiva,
when was the moment that the witnesses existed. But the other way
of saying it is, the point of בית דין beis din validating
is not to give it greater weight as a שטר. shtar It's
just to say this is not a forgery. It's allowing it to
serve as the שטר shtar that it was without it being challenged.
But their signatures don't create—give it a different, you know, a different
weight than it had before. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ערב היוצא אחר חיתום שטרות. Areiv hayotzei achar chitumei shtaros. Now we
get to the last point, which is going back to the idea
of a guarantor. If a guarantor signs after the witnesses, the position
of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael was that the fact that he signs
means that he's obligating himself, but there are no liens because it—there
were no witnesses on his—his obligation didn't have witnesses on it. It
was after the witnesses to the שטר. shtar And then בן ננס
Ben Nanas says, "I'm going to assume from the fact that he
signed afterwards that he only agreed to be an ערב areiv after
the money was loaned." And if that's true, then he's not obligated
at all. Okay? Which is a very powerful illustration of somebody choking
somebody. Like we discussed yesterday, what was the—it's on a text and
then his is underneath. Yeah, that's the case. Yeah. Here's my שטר,
shtar it's the same שטר shtar used yesterday. Okay. Michael owes Doe
a thousand dollars and here are the witnesses. And then afterwards it
says, you know, "I, David, agreed to—agreed to have been a guarantor
for Michael." And David like signs his name. Okay. So David's obligation
doesn't have witnesses on it. So my right to collect from David
doesn't come with liens on David's property. That's what רבי ישמעאל Rebbi
Yishmael says. But בן ננס Ben Nanas says the fact that you
wrote it at the bottom of the שטר, shtar I'm going to
assume that that meant that Michael had already—you had already lent Michael
money, you had the שטר, shtar you were then pressuring Michael to
pay, and Michael didn't have the money and David stepped in and
agreed after the fact to be the guarantor. And then בן ננס
Ben Nanas says if you agree to be an ערב areiv after
the fact, you're not—you're not obligated at all. Okay. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב קודם חיתום שטרות גובה
מנכסים משועבדים. Amar Rav kodem chitumei shtaros gove minechasim meshubadim. If you
write it before the witnesses sign, then it's like a שטר shtar,
on the ערב areiv himself and then that gives you liens even
on the ערב's areiv property. ולאחר חיתום שטרות גובה מנכסים בני חורין,
Velachar chitumei shtaros gove minechasim bnei chorin, then you get from unencumbered
property, which is pretty much the straight פסק psak of רבי ישמעאל,
Rebbi Yishmael, just spelling it out. וזימנין אמר רב, Vezimnin amar Rav,
and there were times that רב Rav would say, אפילו קודם חיתום
שטרות אינו גובה אלא מנכסים בני חורין, afilu kodem chitumei shtaros eino
gove ela minechasim bnei chorin, even if you write it before the
witnesses sign, it's never really a שטר on the ערב. areiv. It's
only a שטר against the לווה. loveh. You never have liens. Now
קשיא דרב אדרב. kashya deRav a-deRav. So is רב Rav. contradicting himself?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא. la kashya. It's not a
contradiction. הא דכתב ביה פלוני ערב הא דכתב ביה ופלוני ערב. Ha
dechasav bei ploni areiv ha dechasav bei u-ploni areiv. So the שטר
where it has that David is the guarantor, does it say, "Michael
borrowed a thousand dollars from Doe and David agreed to be the
guarantor," signatures? That means it's all one testimony and the signatures are
going on the entirety of the testimony, so it's also a שטר
against David. If it says, "Michael borrowed a thousand dollars from Doe.
David is the guarantor," witnesses, then somehow I wrote The witnesses are
only testifying to the core part of the שטר *shtar* that Michael
borrowed the money, David being the guarantor is not part of the
direct testimony of the witnesses, which is a strange idea. Okay. What
was it? A different wording? The vav. You have and David is
the guarantor, which makes it one big statement and the witnesses are
testifying to everything, then it’s also the שטר *shtar* against you. If
there’s no vav, Michael borrowed a thousand dollars, period. David is the
guarantor, period. Signed by the witnesses, then we say it’s only a
שטר *shtar* against Michael. It’s not a שטר *shtar* against David. Okay.
And why are the witnesses signing after it says David is the
guarantor? I mean maybe I don’t know, maybe it’s enough to prove
that David owes the money, but not a formal שטר *shtar* to
give me lien. It’s a strange idea. I don’t understand it. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. ורבי יוחנן אמר *v'Rabbi
Yochanan amar* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, אחד זה ואחד זה
אינו גובה מנכסים משועבדים *echad zeh v'echad zeh eino goveh minichasim meshubadim*.
So even if it says and David is the guarantor, it’s not
a שטר *shtar* against David. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ואף
על גב דכתיב ביה ופלוני ערב u'ploni areiv *v'af al gav de'ketiv
bei up'loni arev* even if it says and so and so is
the guarantor, that’s not part of the testimony of the שטר *shtar*,
which is bizarre. What do you mean it’s not part of the
testimony of the שטר *shtar*? So מתיב רבא *mative Rava*. So רבא
*Rava* challenges. אדם החתום על שאילת שלום she'eilas shalom. בגט פסול passul
*adam hachatum al she’ilat shalom b’get pasul*. This is a very another
strange idea. It says here I am, I divorce my wife, you
know, הרי זה גיטך *harei zeh giteich*, whatever, you know, ואת תהא
מותרת לכל אדם *v’at t’hei muteret le’chol adam*, you know, מן יומא
דנן ולעלם *min yoma dnan u’le’alam*. Oh, and by the way, say
hi to Cheryl when you get a chance, okay? And then the
witnesses sign. So we say it’s not a good גט get *get*
because maybe all the witnesses were saying was, oh yeah, say hi
to Cheryl for us all also. Okay. And maybe they weren’t signing
to the actual testimony of the גט get, *get*, which seems like
a complete rabbinic concern. Like how could you say such a thing?
What does it mean to testify to find out how Cheryl is
doing? So it says, okay, ואמר רבי אבהו *v’amar Rabbi Abbahu* and
רבי אבהו *Rabbi Abbahu* said, לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן *ledidi
meforasha li minei de’Rabbi Yochanan*, that ruling. So anyway, so the question
is, oh, and he clarifies, wait, where is רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
here? Oh, so what’s the problem? Oh, so the problem is that
if in that case we say that the witnesses are going on
the say hi part, so if you have and David is an
ערב areiv *arev*, how could we say that the witnesses are not
also going on that part of the שטר *shtar*? Now of course
there’s a difference. In one case you say maybe it was only
going on the bottom part. Here we have to say it definitely
was going on the part that referred to David in order to
collect to collect from David. But the point is that when we
have something extraneous, and concern David being a guarantor is not that
extraneous written, we don’t assume that the witnesses are not referring to
that line that’s in the document. So let’s see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says. גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this. So it says,
ואמר רבי אבהו לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן *v’amar Rabbi Abbahu
ledidi meforasha li minei de’Rabbi Yochanan*. Ah, here’s the explanation I have
for רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, why he says that the person never
becomes a guarantor and how that’s different than the גט *get* case.
שאילו פסול passul *she’ilu pasul*. If I say, ask how Cheryl is
doing, then it’s פסול *pasul*. Then it’s like a separate line. ושאילו
כשר *v’she’ilu kasher*. But if you say and ask, then it’s כשר
*kasher*, then it’s one testimony. So that’s the interesting פלוני ערב ploni
areiv ופלוני ערב u'ploni areiv *ploni arev u’ploni arev*. Now by the
way, it’s not exactly the same because here the question is, if
you say, here’s the case of the גט *get*, okay, and it
says ושאילו *v’she’ilu* and ask after whatever Rachel and here’s the signature
or whatever Cheryl, okay, then we say it’s one unit and it’s
כשר *kasher*, right? And it’s going on everything and it’s כשר *kasher*.
If you had it say שאילו *she’ilu*, we would say it’s two
units, you have the גט *get* and you have the שאילת שלום
she'eilas shalom *she’ilat shalom* and it’s פסול *pasul* because why? Because the
witnesses are only going on that part, right? That’s the גט *get*
case. But in the case of the ערב areiv *arev*, if you
have here the loan and then you have ופלוני ערב areiv *u’ploni
arev*, then you say it’s all one thing, one and it’s all
one big שטר *shtar* and there are שיעבודים *shibbudim*, right? There are
liens even on the ערב areiv, *arev*. If you have it like
this, right here’s the loan and you said פלוני ערב ploni areiv,
*ploni arev*, what do you say? You’re saying this is the שטר
*shtar*, right? So here you’re saying the שטר *shtar* is only the
bottom to פסול *pasul* the גט *get*. Here you’re saying the שטר
*shtar* obviously is the core part of it is the top. By
comparison. And this should still be כשר because the signatures should still
be going on the core part. תוספות Tosafos points out like obviously
this whole thing by גט is a חומרה, chumra, okay, because anyway
it's a pretty absurd to say you're signing on שאילת שלום. But
the point still being that if here we acknowledge a difference that
when it's one big thing we're not going to פסול the גט,
even though when it's two things that we'll פסול because we'll say
maybe it's only going on the bottom, so certainly here when you're
dealing not with how שאילת שלום was doing but you're saying David
is a guarantor and you have a ו, vav, obviously it should
be one big שטר and it should create liens on David's property.
So we're going to say אין הכי נמי. ein hachi nami. So
the גמרא Gemara, is going to say like this. So הכא נמי
דכתיב פלוני ערב. hacha nami dekasiv ploni areiv. You're right. So the
case that Rabbi Yochanan says that it's not a lien against David
is when it doesn't say and David, it just says David is
the guarantor. So the גמרא says: אי הכי היינו דרב? ee hachi
hainu d'Rav? So that's the same thing רב Rav. said. So Rabbi
Yochanan is not, you know, is not saying oh no no no,
even in that case you don't have liens. He's just saying the
same thing רב said. If you said פלוני ערב areiv, you don't
have liens, ופלוני ערב areiv you do. So the גמרא says: היינו
דרב? hainu d'Rav? אימא וכן אמר רבי יוחנן. eima v'chein amar Rabbi
Yochanan. Fine. So say Rabbi Yochanan said the same thing as רב.
We thought Rabbi Yochanan what he said 'you don't have liens' meant
even if you had the ו vav you don't have liens. And
now we say no, he's really just saying the same thing as
רב. Without the ו vav it's a separate statement and you don't,
with the ו vav it's one statement and you do. Now again,
even without the ו, vav, it's hard to say that the witnesses
are not testifying to the fact that you are the guarantor and
presumably I can use the שטר to force you to pay. It
certainly is evidence to that. The question is does it have the
status of a שטר vis-a-vis you? Since it primarily was written vis-a-vis
Michael and to create liens on Michael's property, do I say that
it functions not only as proof, but as a שטר vis-a-vis you
to create liens on your property? And there as long as there's
some break and it's not a ו vav that's wrapping it all
together, we'll say that it won't be a שטר against you. It
might be that we just make that difference in order to help
protect the poor guarantor. He's already doing this nice act of protecting,
you know, of being nice and stepping up to the plate, maybe
we want to limit the cases that he's really going to be
like fully exposed to go be מנכסים בני חורין. m'nechasim b'nechorim. I
understand, but you know, and also like right, how much do the
לקוחות lekuchos, maybe we're trying to protect the לקוחות, lekuchos how much
do they find out that, you know, not that he borrowed money
but he was a guarantor for somebody else's loans and I
have to be careful about buying his property, right?
So it might be we're trying to protect the לקוחות lekuchos more
as well also. Okay, now the גמרא says like this: they know
the difference between ופלוני ערב areiv versus פלוני ערב, arev, you know,
this is... Right. I know, so I'm saying that that to me
seems very like a hairsplitting thing, I could make a formalistic difference,
but I'm wondering again if there's some policy that's driving it about
trying to protect לקוחות more in that case. Let's wrap up: ומעשה
בא לפני רבי ישמעאל. u'maiseh ba lifnei Rabbi Yishmael. Now here was
the story that a case came for Rabbi Yishmael, the signature was
at the bottom after the witnesses. He said okay, there's no liens,
but at least the ערב arev is liable. And בן ננס Ben
Nanas says the ערב arev, isn't even liable. And says why not?
So he gave this very pow... you know, like powerful image of
somebody who's choking somebody, said Michael, pay me up my loan! And
David said, leave him alone, I'll agree to pay you. So says
David is just doing it to stop me from pressuring Michael, he
doesn't really mean to obligate himself. So if he signed after at
the bottom of the שטר, we'll assume that means that he agreed
to pay after I lent money to Michael. And since that's what
it is, he's really not obligating himself to me. Okay, that's what
בן ננס Ben Nanas says. So the גמרא says like this: Right.
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbah bar bar
Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan: אף על פי שקילס רבי ישמעאל לבן ננס.
af al pi she-killess Rabbi Yishmael l'Ben Nanas. So then Rabbi Yishmael
ended by saying: oh, if you want to become smart, learn דיני
ממונות. dinei mamanos. And actually use the nice language of business. If
you want to go into a good business of learning תורה, the
way you make good money or good תורה out of, you know,
good חכמה chochma from learning is go into the learning of דיני
ממונות. dinei mamanos. And if you want to learn דיני ממונות dinei
mamanos well, you should apprentice yourself to בן ננס. Ben Nanas. He
was just such a powerful image. So he says even though he
was praising בן ננס, Ben Nanas, הלכה כמותו. halacha k'masoh. We rule
like Rabbi Yishmael that if you sign after the witnesses, you do
obligate yourself, there are no liens, but you do obligate yourself. Even
if you agree to be an ערב arev after the money was
lent out. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya l'hu. Now they asked the question: בחנק
מה לי אמר רבי ישמעאל? b'chanok ma lei amar Rabbi Yishmael? Let's
say it was literally a case, not just a metaphor or whatever,
or not just an analogy, but here I am, I'm literally choking
Michael, okay, and David runs in and he says: no, no, no,
I'll be an ערב, arev, okay, would Rabbi Yishmael say there too
he's obligated? Or he would think in this case he's too...? Okay,
so, תא שמע, ta shema, come hear: דאמר רבי יעקב אמר רבי
יוחנן: d'amar Rabbi Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan: חולק היה רבי ישמעאל אף
בחנק. cholok haya Rabbi Yishmael af b'chanok. Nope, yet Rabbi Yishmael would
say even if I was choking Michael, once David agrees to be
an ערב, arev he's an ערב arev no matter what reasons are
motivating him. Which is interesting if you think about yesterday. We haven't
had a chance to speak to it yet. Okay, so so besides
which, well I'm not being תלוי talui David. But whatever. No, but
if you think about yesterday, the idea that if somebody is agreeing
to be an ערב arev for a כתובה, kesubah, he's not obligated
because he's just trying to get the couple married, right? So we...
It would seem this would be a similar point, I mean, you
know, but maybe it's like a lo plug לא פלוג, lo plug,
we can't go figuring out what were the different things that motivated
David. At the end of the day, he agrees to be an
arev ערב, arev he's liable. Okay, so now the Gemara גמרא says,
okay, now Halacha k'moso הלכה כמותו Halacha k'moso or ein Halacha k'moso
אין הלכה כמותו? ein Halacha k'moso? Fine, now do we rule like
Rabbi Ishmael ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael in the case of when the
loveh לוה loveh is being literally choked? Like fine, Rabbi Ishmael ר'
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say that, you know, yes, even in that
case he's liable, but do we rule that way? So tashma תא
שמע, tashma, come in here, deki'ata Rabin amar Rabbi Yochanan דכי אתא
רבין אמר ר' יוחנן, deki'ata Rabin amar Rabbi Yochanan, when Rabin רבין
Rabin came from Eretz Yisrael ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said in
the name of Rabbi Yochanan ר' יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: cholak haya Rabbi
Ishmael af bechanuk חולק היה ר' ישמעאל אף בחנוק, cholak haya Rabbi
Ishmael af bechanuk, Rabbi Ishmael ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would disagree with
Benanas בן ננס Benanas even when the guy is being choked and
say that the arev ערב arev does obligate himself, v'halacha k'moso af
bechanuk והלכה כמותו אף בחנוק, v'halacha k'moso af bechanuk, and we rule
that way, which again makes it interesting compared to the case of
the kesuvah כתובה, kesuvah, but maybe it's like lo plug לא פלוג,
lo plug, we can't go ahead and figure out every single case
what motivated the guarantor, and once the guarantor agrees, he's liable. Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel: chanuk v'kanu miyado חנוק וקנו מידו, chanuk v'kanu miyado, now
we're trying to pull back. If a guy was being choked, meaning
and the guarantor stepped in, then the guarantor only obligates himself if
he did a kinyan קנין kinyan to show how serious he was,
like the handkerchief. Okay, mishtabed משתעבד. mishtabed. Okay, mikhlal d'arev b'alma lo
bay kinyan מכלל דערב בעלמא לא בעי קנין, mikhlal d'arev b'alma lo
bay kinyan, in a normal case a guarantor does not need a
kinyan קנין, kinyan, just verbally he obligates himself. We referred to this
before, but literally the Gemara גמרא waited till the last two lines
of the Masechet מסכת Masechet to discuss what is the act that
obligates the arev ערב, is it verbal, or does he need to
do a kinyan קנין? kinyan? So here it sounds like he only
needs to do a kinyan קנין kinyan if he steps in at
the last minute to, you know, to because the guy's being choked,
whether literally or figuratively. But otherwise, verbally would be enough. So Gemara
גמרא says, mikhlal d'arev b'alma lo bay kinyan מכלל דערב בעלמא לא
בעי קנין, mikhlal d'arev b'alma lo bay kinyan, u'pligi d'Rav Nachman ופליגי
דרב נחמן, u'pligi d'Rav Nachman, that argues on Rav Nachman רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. D'amar Rav Nachman דאמר רב נחמן, D'amar Rav Nachman, Rav
Nachman רב נחמן Rav Nachman says, arev d'be din hu d'lo bay
kinyan ערב דבי דין הוא דלא בעי קנין, arev d'be din hu
d'lo bay kinyan, if the guy agrees to be an arev ערב
and it's being somehow supervised or assigned by the court, I'm not
exactly sure what that role is, then the fact that the court
is giving you that role gives enough weight to it and maybe
makes you take it sort of serious because you're, you know, because
you're honored by the court to take this role, then you're obligated
even without a kinyan קנין. kinyan. Ha d'alma bay kinyan הא דבעלמא
בעי קנין, Ha d'alma bay kinyan, but normally an arev ערב, yes,
even an arev ערב who is a normal arev ערב and not
at the time that the guy's being pressured, maybe even at the
time of the loan, because that was the one exception of a
court-appointed arev ערב you need a kinyan קנין. kinyan. So now we
have a kinyan קנין kinyan is needed all the time, or kinyan
קנין kinyan is needed if the arev ערב steps in at the
last minute to, you know, to because the guy's being choked, whether
literally or figuratively. But otherwise, verbally would be enough. And now let's
see the conclusion of the Gemara גמרא. V'hilchesa והלכתא, V'hilchesa, and Michael
could be very happy that a masechet מסכת masechet ends with a
hilchesa הלכתא. hilchesa. V'hilchesa והלכתא: V'hilchesa: arev b'shas matan maos lo bay
kinyan ערב בשעת מתן מעות לא בעי קנין. arev b'shas matan maos
lo bay kinyan. If you're when the money is being lent, verbally
is enough. This is like the difference we made before, because then
obviously you are, the money is being lent because of your say-so,
and you really are taking the responsibility because David said he would
guarantee is why I am willing to lend money to Michael. So
that really creates a serious weight of responsibility on David, he's obligating
himself even just verbally there. Right, achar matan maos אחר מתן מעות,
Achar matan maos, afterwards, where I've already lent the money, I'm not
it's not relying on him, he's maybe just doing it to stop
me from forcing Michael and giving and pressuring him, bay kinyan בעי
קנין. bay kinyan. That needs the kinyan קנין, kinyan, that's like the
first statement of the Gemara גמרא, that the kinyan קנין kinyan is
needed only in the Benanas בן ננס Benanas type of a case
when David steps in after the money has been lent. Okay, arev
d'be din v'arev d'be din lo bay kinyan ערב דבי דין וערב
דבי דין לא בעי קנין arev d'be din v'arev d'be din lo
bay kinyan doesn't need a kinyan קנין kinyan whenever the person is
assigned as an arev ערב through the court. D'behahi d'heiman lei gmar
u'mishabed lei דבההיא דהימן ליה גמר ומשעבד ליה, D'behahi d'heiman lei gmar
u'mishabed lei, by that pleasure that he gets and he knows that
he's trusted by Beis Din בית דין, Beis Din, he agrees to
take that role whether, you know, even with even just verbally, even
without a kinyan קנין. kinyan. Hadran alach get pashut uselika lach masechet
Bava Batra הדרן עלך גט פשוט וסליקא לך מסכת בבא בתרא. Hadran
alach get pashut uselika lach masechet Bava Batra. So yasher koach יישר
כוח yasher koach to everybody and all of finishing Bava Batra בבא
בתרא Bava Batra and all of Seder Nezikin סדר נזיקין. Seder Nezikin.
And tomorrow we begin Sanhedrin סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and we will be doing
it with a little Yerushalmi ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. So we're going to be
starting with Yerushalmi Mishulav ירושלמי משולב, Yerushalmi Mishulav, I'll send out like
the Yerushalmi ירושלמי Yerushalmi text, I'll make copies. Okay, we'll start with
that. Yeah, I'll do that. Okay, see you all tomorrow.